Preliminary Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office. Records, 1947-1999 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office. records 1947-1999 and undated
J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office.
Extent: 48,972 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00706
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Co. Archives: Detroit Office Records was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1989-2002.
Historical Note
The J. Walter Thompson Company was founded in New York, N.Y., in 1864, and is one of the world's largest advertising agencies.
Collection Overview
Collection (accessions from 1991-1999) is minimally processed. Contains miscellaneous files from the Detroit office, including Ford and competitive collateral literature; tearsheets; Ford and competitive price lists and specs; Ford historical files and publications; internal office publications; EPA files and reports. Includes photographs, slides, and two film reels. Most items refer to the domestic Ford account, as well as to trucks rather than cars. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising and Marketing History. A container list was created only for accession 93-015.
Addition (02-202)(4872 items, 13.2 lin. ft.; dated 1986-1999 and undated) is minimally processed. Contains primarily color transparencies for Ford dealer catalogs (by model and year, 1993-1997) and photographs of Ford car and truck interior and exteriors (1999). Also includes final versions of Ford dealer catalogs (1992-1999); local Ford Dealer Association campaign mockups (by city/district, 1990-1996); Ford trucks campaign materials (1991-1998); and campaign mockups for Gerry Baby Products (1989) and Hooks Drug Stores (1990). A container list was created for this accession.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office; Ford Motor Company; United States. Environmental Protection Agency; Advertising -- History; Advertising agencies -- History; Advertising -- Automobiles -- United States; Ford automobile -- Marketing; Ford automobile -- Marketing -- History; Automobiles -- Marketing; Automobiles -- United States; Photographs; Slides; Motion pictures; Color transparencies; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Accession 93-015
  Unpublished materials less than 15 years old are closed to non-JWT researchers.
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1961-1986 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1960-1967 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1963-1967 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1965-1984 (Box 4)
  - Historical Files. Ford truck components 1960s (Box 5)
    Engineering and standards information for axles, engines, misc. other components, and Recreational Vehicles.
  - Collateral literature, Ford trucks, 1960s (Box 6)
  - NADA, used car price guides, early 1980s (Box 7)
  - Ford Dealer, Truck comparison information booklets, 1954-1971 (Box 8)
  - Competitive Collateral literature, trucks, 1977-1987 (Box 9)
  - For Sales and Promotional Literature
  - Competitive Collateral literature, Ford trucks 1978-1986 (Box 10)
  - Competitive Advertisements, Trucks, 1970s-1980s (Box 11)
    - Mack
    - Mazda
    - Peterbuilt
    - Plymouth
    - Toyota
    - Dodge
    - GMC
    - Datsun
    - Miscellaneous
    - Recreational Vehicles, Older Trucks
    - Brockway
    - Chevrolet
    - Freight Linear
    - Jeep
    - Kenworth
  - Competitive Advertisements, Trucks, 1970s-1980s(cont.) (Box 12)
    - White
  - Canadian Advertisements, Ford trucks
    - Fleet
    - Leasing
    - Motor-Homes
    - Rent-a-Car
    - Campers
    - Maximum Duty Trucks
    - Heavy Duty Trucks
  - Competitive truck articles
    Misc. models. Clippings from various sources.
  - Competitive Collateral Literature (Box 13)
    - Chevrolet Trucks, 1958-1971
      Show room catalogs.
  - Competitive Collateral Literature (cont.) (Box 14)
    - Chevrolet trucks, 1970-1978
  - Competitive Collateral Literature (Box 15)
    - Dodge trucks, 1973-1988
  - Competitive Collateral Literature (Box 16)
    - Dodge trucks, 1983, 1986-1987
  - Ford Collateral Literature
    - Heavy Trucks
    - Tractors
  - Press Releases, Ford 1960-1968 (Box 17)
  - Competitive Collateral Literature
    - Misc. Trucks 1963-1975
      Direct Mail.
  - Competitive Collateral Literature (cont.) (Box 18)
    - Misc. Trucks 1965-1966
      Direct mail.
  - Newsletter
    - "Sales Workshop News-For Ford Dealers and Salesman"
  - Newsletter
    - "Ford Science Front," 1964-1968
  - Photograph-Ford trucks and Fire Engines
  - Ford truck catalogs, 1968-1976
  - Ford truck catalogs, 1977-1980 (Box 19)
  - Competitive Collateral Literature, Ford trucks, 1951-1959 (Box 20)
    Chiefly dealer catalogs.
  - Competitive Collateral Literature, Ford trucks, 1960-1965 (Box 21)
  - Competitive Collateral Literature-Ford trucks, 1966-1976 (Box 22)
  - Competitive Collateral Literature-Ford trucks, 1966-1976 (cont.) (Box 23)
    Sales catalogs, accessories catalogs. Misc. other collateral literature. No files for 1971-1972.
  - Photographs, Ford Cars, 1952-1959 (Box 24)
    Misc. photographs of Ford cars, station wagons, engines, and components.
  - Photographs, Ford Cars, 1947-1951 (cont.) (Box 25)
    Misc. photographs of Ford cars, station wagons, engines, and components
  - Ford manufacturing and engineering files
  - Recreational Vehicles
    - Product Information
    - Press Releases
  - Bottling Industry
    - Sales and Promotion Literature
  - Historical Files-Engines, axles, filters
  - Competitive Comparisons, Ford Trucks, 1950s-1960s
  - Competitive Advertisements, Trucks, 1976
    Tearsheets and direct mail.
  - Publications (Box 26)
    - "Ford Times," 1972-1977
    - "Ford Truck Times," 1968-1976
    - "Clues," 1952
      Ford Dealer Publication.
  - Publications (cont.) (Box 27)
  - Competitive Advertisements and Collateral Literature, 1963-1965 (Box 28)
  - Thunderbird
  - Competitive Advertisements
    - Direct Mail, 1968
    - Trucks, 1970s
  - Collateral literature, Ford, 1970s-1980s
  - Publications (Box 29)
    - "Clues" 1956-1966
      Car club magazine, promotional publication.
  - Collateral literature, Ford, 1987-1988 (Box 30)
    Cars and trucks, duplicates discarded.
  - Collateral literature, Ford, 1984-1986 (Box 31)
  - Collateral literature, Ford, 1981-1983 (Box 32)
    Chiefly truck catalogs.
  - Collateral literature, Ford, 1950-1957 (Box 33)
    Chiefly dealer catalogues for cars.
  - Collateral literature, Ford, 1957-1960 (Box 34)
  - Collateral literature, Ford, 1957-1960 (cont.) (Box 35)
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1969-1970
    Various models.
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1969-1977(cont.) (Box 36)
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1979-1973 (Box 37)
    Various models, WHQ Construction photos, accessories, details, engines.
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1979-1973(cont.) (Box 38)
  - Competitive Direct Mail (Box 39)
    Miscellaneous manufacturers.
  - Truck price historical file, Ford, 1970s-1980s (Box 40)
  - Rapid Specs. 1986
  - Rapid Specs, Price lists, 1986 (Box 41)
  - Competitive price information
    - Toyota
    - Volkswagen
    - Nissan
    - Mazda
  - Competitive price information (cont.) (Box 42)
  - Truck price historical file, Ford, 1980
  - Ford truck catalogs 1971-1972 (Box 43)
  - Truck Names file (Box 44)
  - EPA Files, 1974-1976, 1978-1979
  - EPA Files, 1977, 1980 (Box 45)
  - EPA Files, 1981 (Box 46)
  - Competitive Collateral Literature, GMC truck, 1969-1973
  - Competitive Collateral Literature, GMC truck, 1980-1986 (Box 47)
  - Competitive Collateral Literature, trucks, GMC 1987 Dodge 1962-1972 (Box 48)
  - Competitive Collateral Literature, trucks, GMC 1974-1978 Dodge 1970-1971 (Box 49)
  - Ford Truck shop manuals, 1970s
  - Competitors comparison price lists, 1970s-1980s (Box 50)
  - Ford truck shop manuals, 1970s (Box 51)
  - Competitors price lists, 1980-1985 (Box 52)
  - Competitors price lists, 1980-1985 (cont.) (Box 53)
  - Ford service manuals, specs, 1957-1969 (Box 54)
  - Competitors price lists, early 1980
  - Collateral literature, Ford heavy truck, 1964-1968
  - Collateral literature, Ford truck, 1960s
  - Collateral literature, Ford truck, 1960s (cont.) (Box 55)
  - Collateral literature, Ford trucks, 1958-1964 (Box 56)
  - Competitive collateral literature, trucks, 1969-1973 (Box 57)
  - Fleet management news, 1969-1971 (Box 58)
  - Competitive collateral literature and photographs, trucks, International Harvester, 1960sand 1970s
  - Competitive collateral literature and photographs, trucks, Jeep, Kenworth, Mack, 1960s and 1970s (Box 59)
  - Competitive collateral literature, trucks, GMC, 1960s (Box 60)
  - Competitive collateral literature, trucks, Mazda, Mitsubishi, 1980s
  - Competitive collateral literature, trucks, Mazda, Mitsubishi, 1980s (cont.) (Box 61)
  - Competitive collateral literature, trucks, mostly Chevrolet, 1980s (Box 62)
  - Competitive collateral literature, Chevrolet trucks, 1987 (Box 63)
  - "Automotive News," almanac issues 1959-1966, 1974; Ford 75th Anniversary issue, 1978
  - Body builders layout book, Dodge, 1966, 1970;Chevrolet 1968
  - Ford Ranger preliminary engineering specs, 1983
  - Manuals, Ford trucks, 1970s-1980s
  - Competitive collateral literature, Mitsubishi, 1987 (Box 64)
  - Reports, office files--Ford Research, mostly 1980s (Box 65)
  - Reports, office files--Ford Research, mostly 1980s (Box 66)
  - Collateral literature, Ford heavy truck
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1987
  - Reports, office files--Ford Research, mostly 1980s (cont.) (Box 67)
  - Collateral literature, Ford heavy truck
  - Photographs, Ford trucks, 1987
  - "Ford Truck Times," 1968-1971 (Box 68)
  - "Clues," 1950s
  - Competitive Truck direct mail, 1960s
  - Competitive Truck direct mail, 1960s (cont.) (Box 69)
  - Competitive Truck collateral literature, 1960s-1970s
  - "Hildy's Blue Book for Ford Trucks," 1940s-1960s (Box 70)
  - "Hildy's Blue Book for Ford Trucks," 1950s-1980s (Box 71)
  - EPA Files, 1980s (Box 72)
  - Automotive News
  - Ford options, specs files (Box 73)
  - Ford historical ads (Box 74)
  - Ford truck product info, 1960s-1970s
  - Misc. slides and photographs, 1970s-1980s
  - AMA Automotive Facts and Figures, 1950s (Box 75)
  - Ford truck manuals, 1950s-1960s
  - Ford historical files: tractors, accessories, firefighting, transmissions, safety, etc. (Box 76)
  - Ford historical files: tractors, accessories, firefighting, transmissions, safety, etc. (Box 77)
  - Blaise Newman reports, files: includes Ford and other accounts, new business, etc.
  - Blaise Newman reports, files: includes Ford and other accounts, new business, etc. (cont.) (Box 78)
  - Blaise Newman reports, files: includes Ford and other accounts, new business, etc. (cont.) (Box 79)
  - Sean Neald (Ford Domestic operations) files
  - Advertising plans, Ford car (Taurus, Tempo), 1980s (Box 80)
  - Newsletters: (Box 81)
    - WPP Group, 1989-1990
    - "J. Walter Thompson News," 1980s
    - "Detroit Thompson Times," 1982-1986
    - "JWT Detroiter," 1970s
  - Health Alliance Plan studies, 1987-1988 (Box 82)
  - Ford yearly catalogs, 1983-1984
  - Oversized material removed from Boxes 15, 16, 22, 47, 49, 64, 69, and 75 (Box 83)
  - 1958 Thunderbird drawings
  - Final Results, Ford Truck Economy Run (c.1960s?) (Box 84)
  - Superior school bus brochure, 1961
  - Ford yearly catalogs, 1984-1985
  - Ford, video tape reel, "In Search of 200 m.p.h." Lyn St. James/Fast Lady--Track, commercials edited out, 1987 (Box 85)
  - Ford, video tape reel, "The Man from Thunder Road", 1988 (Box 86)
- Accession 2002-0202
  - Contents of Box 1: (Box 1)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1993-1994
  - Contents of Box 2: (Box 2)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1993-1994
  - Contents of Box 3: (Box 3)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1995
  - Contents of Box 4: (Box 4)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1995-1996
  - Contents of Box 5: (Box 5)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1996
    - Ford Dealer Association, local campaign mockups, 1996
  - Contents of Box 6: (Box 6)
    - Ford dealer catalog mockups, 1993-1994
    - Gerry Baby Products campaign mockup, 1989
    - Hooks Drug Stores campaign mockup, 1990
    - Ford Dealer Association, local campaign and logo art (by city/district), 1995
  - Contents of Box 7: (Box 7)
    - Ford Dealer Association files and mockups (by city/district), 1989-1990
  - Contents of Box 8: (Box 8)
    - Ford Dealer Association files and mockups (by city/district), 1990-1991
    - Competitive pop-up and 3-D advertising examples
  - Contents of Box 9: (Box 9)
    - Ford truck campaign materials, 1994-1998
  - Contents of Box 10: (Box 10)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies and flowcharts (by model name and year), 1996-1997
  - Contents of Box 11: (Box 11)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1993-1997
  - Contents of Box 12: (Box 12)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1997
  - Contents of Box 13: (Box 13)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1997
  - Contents of Box 14: (Box 14)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1996-1997
  - Contents of Box 15: (Box 15)
    - Ford dealer catalog transparencies (by model name and year), 1997
    - Booth Demographics Report, Newspapers, 1989
    - Ford dealer catalogs, commercial trucks, 1992-1994
  - Contents of Box 16: (Box 16)
    - Ford dealer catalogs, 1992-1995
    - Ford Motorsports advertisements, 1986-1991
  - Contents of Box 17: (Box 17)
    - Ford dealer catalogs, 1996-1999
  - Contents of Oversize Box 18: (Box 18)
    - Ford original film transparencies, car and truck interiors and exteriors, 1999
  - Contents of Oversize Box 19: (Box 19)
    - Ford original film transparencies, car and truck interiors and exteriors, 1999
  - Contents of Oversize Box 20: (Box 20)
    - Ford original film transparencies, car and truck interiors and exteriors, 1999
  - Contents of Oversize Box 21: (Box 21)
    - Ford original film transparencies, car and truck interiors and exteriors, 1999
  - Contents of Oversize Box 22: (Box 22)
    - Ford original film transparencies, car and truck interiors and exteriors, 1999
    - Ford Truck advertising, 1996
    - Milwaukee district campaign materials, undated
    - Ford Dealer Association campaigns and logos, undated
    - Ford dealer catalogs, trucks, 1991-1996